Guide to the Carl L. Lokke Papers, 1913-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carl L. Lokke papers 1913-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lokke, Carl Ludwig, 1897-1960.
16.1 linear feet Extent: Approximately 4000 Items
Archivist and historian; chief of Foreign Affairs Branch at the U.S. National Archives. Collection consists of the biographical and professional files of Carl Ludwig Lokke, who was on the staff of the National Archives for many years. Material includes copies of his own research papers and many folders of research notes on his specialty, 18th century French colonialism in the West Indies colonies, and more specifically on the life and career of colonial administrator Baron Pierre-Victor Malouet, who was active mainly in French Guiana. There are also many transcriptions and photocopies of primary documents from archives in France and other repositories, as well as some microfilms. Other material includes Lokke's work files from the National Archives.
RL.00821
Language: Material in English and French
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Carl L. Lokke Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1964 and 1968.
Biographical Note
Archivist and historian; chief of Foreign Affairs Branch at the U.S. National Archives.
Collection Overview
The Carl L. Lokke Papers are dated between 1918 and 1968, and consist of the biographical and professional files of Carl Ludwig Lokke, who was on the staff of the National Archives for many years. Material includes copies of his own research papers and many folders of research notes on his specialty, 18th century French colonialism in the West Indies colonies, and more specifically on the life and career of colonial administrator Baron Pierre-Victor Malouet, who was mainly active in French Guiana. There are also many transcriptions and photocopies of primary documents from archives in France and other repositories, as well as some microfilms and a few journal issues and other printed material. A series of alphabetical fiels contains writings by other authors and is arranged by country. Other files contain material related to Lokke's archival career, including files relating to the National Archives, and service awards.
Subject Headings
Colonial administrators -- West Indies; France -- Colonies -- History; France -- History -- 18th century; French Guiana -- History; Historians -- United States -- Correspondence; Lokke, Carl Ludwig, 1897-1960; Malouet, Pierre-Victor, baron, 1740-1814; Microfilms; United States. National Archives and Records Service -- Officials and employees; United States. National Archives and Records Service; West Indies, French -- History
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1918-1960, (6 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1945 (Box 1)
  - Postcards (Box 1)
  - Dissertation correspondence (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1937 (Box 3)
  - 1939-1945 (Box 4)
  - 1946-1951 (Box 5)
  - 1952-1960 (Box 6)
- Research Notes Series, 1926-1958, (2.5 boxes)
  - Printed material (Box 7)
    - Revue Société d'Histoire et de Geographie d'Haiti, 1946-1949 (Box 7)
  - Research notes (Box 7)
  - Black and white photographs (Box 7)
  - Research notes (Box 13)
  - Certificates and awards:
    - General Services Administrative Service Award, 1957 (Box 13)
    - Fellow of the Society of American Archivists, 1958 (Box 13)
  - Clippings, 1926-1958 and undated (Box 14)
  - Record group memos (Box 14)
  - U.S. National Archives (Box 14)
- Biographical and Professional Files Series, 1935-1960, (5 boxes)
  - Personal and family history files (Box 8)
  - U.S. National Archives, 1935-1937 (Box 9)
  - U.S. National Archives, 1941-1944 (Box 10)
  - U.S. National Archives, 1944-1956 (Box 11)
  - U.S. National Archives, 1956-1960 (Box 12)
- French Research Series, (10 boxes)
  Primarily contains unarranged research notes for Lokke's work on Baron Pierre-Victor Malouet, an 18th century French colonial administrator and French colonial policy strategist, active mainly in French Guiana. In addition to secondary source notes and citations, contains photostats and hand-written transcriptions of primary sources.
  - French research files (Box 15-24)
- Writings Series, 1913-1968, (7.5 boxes)
  - Bibliography (Box 25)
  - St. Nicholas magazine, 1913 (Box 25)
  - Dissertation, draft copy (Box 25)
  - Revision of book on French colonies (Box 25)
  - Fauchet Memoire (Box 26)
  - Handbook of Federal World War Agencies, 1943 (Box 26)
  - Alaska article, Collins Encyclopedia (Box 26)
  - Article on Continental Congress Papers (Box 27)
  - Writings, 1949-1959 (Box 28)
  - Writings, 1947, 1959 (Box 29)
  - Writings, 1928-1944 (Box 30)
  - Writings, 1946, 1958 (Box 31)
  - Writings, 1949, 1968 and undated (Box 32)
- Printed Material Series, (6.5 boxes)
  Contains primarily pamphlets and books by authors other than Lokke. Arranged geographically.
  - Alaska (Box 32)
  - Venezuela (Box 32)
  - Great Britain (Box 33)
  - Other foreign countries
    - Italy (Box 33)
    - Japan (Box 33)
    - Montenegro (Box 33)
    - Poland (Box 33)
    - Romania (Box 33)
    - Turkey (Box 33)
  - Scandinavia (Box 33)
  - Spain and Portugese America (Box 33)
  - Various printed material (Box 34)
  - Austria (Box 35)
  - Germany (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 35)
  - Various printed material (Box 36)
  - French Foreign Office report of research (Box 37)
  - Various journals (Box 38)
- Oversize Material, (1 box)
  - Oversize copies of primary sources (Box 39)